What if it was a simple mineral
deficiency leading to people developing
the brain disorder Alzheimer's disease?
Well, there's new compelling evidence
not just in animals, but in human
research like here, where the
researchers of a huge new study measured
the brain levels of lithium in the
brains of humans either without
Alzheimer's with mild cognitive
impairment, so progressively reduced
brain function and finally ad there is
Alzheimer's disease. The researchers
identified a relationship between low
brain lithium levels and both
neurodeenerative conditions relative to
the healthy non-afflicted brain. But
correlation is not causation. So is
lithium the anti-Alzheimer's mineral
that we've been waiting for? Well, to
create some sort of cause and effect
relationship, the researchers used a
common Alzheimer's mouse model and then
either gave one group lithium and the
other they made sure to remain deficient
in lithium. Then they quantified the
number of plaques. These are the clumps
of protein that sit between our brain
cells, our neurons, and interfere with
the molecular communication between
these cells. The researchers here
labeled the plaques in green. I don't
even need to annunciate that. You can
clearly see in the lithium deficient
groups of the DEF there, there's much
more green indicating more of these
disruptive plaques are found in the
brain. Beyond that, the researchers also
did a series of cognitive tests and
confirmed worse performance. So, the
takeaway here is that being low in the
mineral lithium increases plaques in the
brain, which are implicated in
Alzheimer's disease. Okay. Then, do we
supplement with it? Well, the
researchers did exactly that. They gave
the same mice lithium and were able to
significantly reduce the amount of
plaques found in the brain as well as
improve their brain function. But this
extends beyond animal data because there
have been clinical trials that have also
indicated effectiveness of lithium. Now
why is lithium so low in the brain and
could this offer a clue on how to
supplement with it? The main clue in
relation to how lithium acts on the
brain is due to its low levels in the
brain cells themselves. This was awfully
suspicious to the researchers because
what is happening to the available
lithium? Well, they end up arguing that
lithium is attaching to the plaques
themselves. If that's the case, the
brain cells can't access the lithium as
it's bound to these unwanted protein
bundles. So, this offers some clues on
specific supplementation. In fact,
before that though, the researchers also
brought up how lithium can reverse
Alzheimer's link plaque, several other
mechanisms by which lithium deficiency
hurts the brain, and also what they deem
to be the best lithium type. And I also
analyzed a fascinating study on
long-term effects of supplementation on
the brain. I cover all that in the
extended version of the video that
you're watching, which you get as a
physionic insider along with all of
these wonderful perks. The podcast, live
sessions with me, weekly articles, and
more. You can join using the link in the
description. I'll see you on the inside.
These clues on supplementation come from
some further experiments where the
researchers identified which lithium
types are less prone to being
sequestered by the plaques, therefore
keeping them available for the brain
cells. In those experiments, they
identified a clear trend that inorganic
lithium salts like lithium chloride,
carbonate, and so on are less likely to
be effective against Alzheimer's than
organic lithium salts. The researchers
even indicate significant reversal of
Alzheimer's brain degradation from these
lithium salts. To be clear, this is
based on mechanistic data. Now the other
important factor is dosing because while
you might have heard of dosing lithium
for something like bipolar disorder, the
dosing is completely different. In this
situation, we're talking about people
trying to avoid cognitive impairment and
Alzheimer's. The doses are on the
microgram scale, a 1,000fold
difference from clinical bipolar
disorders. So where does that land us in
some? This study directly indicates
there is within brain lithium deficiency
in people experiencing clinical
cognitive decline on the path to
Alzheimer's. Lithium supplementation
reduces or eliminates cognitive decline
with some decent evidence in humans as
well. Lithium used in human studies are
trace doses along the lines of 300 to
400 micrograms of lithium, but there's
plenty more to be done against dementias
like Alzheimer's. So, don't forget to
click right here. But you wouldn't
forget because you got your brain
activated already learning about the
lithium. So, might as well just keep
that streak going,